Finding Aid for Theodore R. Bohn papers
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Theodore R. Bohn Papers 1942-1983 1950s-1960s
Bohn, Theodore R.
0.4 linear feet
2014042 Aa 2
Papers of Honorable Theodore R. Bohn, a Michigan Democratic politician and judge for the 3rd Circuit Court of Wayne County, including civil rights legislation and legal materials regarding immigration reform and labor union organizing from the 1950s-1960s.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Materials acquired from Julia B. Dean (Donor no. 11016 ) in October 2013.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Judge Theodore R. Bohn was born on a farm near Bay City, Michigan. He attended Bay City Junior College and then went on to attain a degree from the University of Minnesota. He moved to Detroit in 1932, and soon began taking night courses at the Detroit College of Law. He started practicing law in Detroit in 1936, and continued to do so for eight years. In 1942, he took a job with the federal Department of Justice, a position he held for five years.
Bohn then returned to private practice in Detroit, and was a partner in a firm specializing in labor law, Rothe, Marston, Edwards & Bohn. Bohn was elected as the Wayne County Democratic Chairman and served for four years. He was also the president of the Michigan Association for Justice in Lansing from 1949-53. Judge Bohn was also an honorary member of the University of Michigan Lawyer's Club beginning in 1955.
Theodore Bohn was appointed to the bench of the Michigan Circuit Court by Governor G. Mennen "Soapy" Williams in 1955, and continued to serve as a judge in the 3rd Judicial Circuit of Wayne County until his retirement in December 1982. Throughout his career, Bohn contributed greatly to Williams' political campaigns, both as Michigan Governor and State Supreme Court Justice. Bohn supported Williams financially, socially and politically, often campaigning on his behalf. The two remained close colleagues throughout Bohn's 27 years as a member of the 3rd Circuit Court of Wayne County.
The Theodore R. Bohn papers is comprised of fourteen folders. The first nine folders contain a variety of materials and formats. The final five folders all contain photographs. This collection contains political correspondence, campaign election materials, photographs, ballots and ephemera from the career of Judge Theodore R. Bohn. Re-election materials and correspondence from Bohn's colleagues are also included, especially material from G. Mennen Williams' various campaigns.
A small run of the Bulletin of the Michigan Committee on Civil Rights is also included, both the state chapter and the Detroit chapter, between the years 1950-1952. In addition, the collection contains pamphlets, speeches and mailings on the subjects of labor organizing, civil rights struggles and resulting anti-discrimination legislation, and immigration policy reform. Also included are newspaper clippings pertaining to the arrests and trials of union leader Jimmy Hoffa in 1967 and 1971.
Subjects:
Bohn, Theodore R.; Civil rights--Michigan.; Elections--Michigan--Detroit.; Hoffa, James R. (James Riddle), 1913-; Judges--Michigan.; Labor unions--Michigan--Detroit.; Michigan. Circuit Court (Wayne County); Political campaigns--Michigan--Detroit.; Williams, G. Mennen, 1911-1988.
Genre Terms:
Ballots.; Clippings.; Correspondence.; Photographs.
- Theodore R. Bohn papers
  - Correspondence, 1952-1983 (scattered dates) (Box 1)
  - Election Campaigns
    - Bohn, 1955-1977 (scattered dates) (Box 1)
    - G. Mennen Williams, 1952-1982 (scattered dates) (Box 1)
    - Other Colleagues (Box 1)
  - Labor Unions, Civil Rights and Immigration Policy Reform (Box 1)
  - Michigan Committee on Civil Rights (MCCR)
    - Bulletin, Convention Notes and Keynote Speech, 1950 & 1952. (Box 1)
    - Detroit Chapter -- Constitution and Bulletin, 1950-1951 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings (Jimmy Hoffa), 1967 and 1971 (Box 1)
  - Obituaries and Funeral Notices (Box 1)
  - Photographs
    - Circuit Court Judges Group Portraits (Box 1)
    - Judicial Appointments & Responsibilities (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous Group Portraits (Box 1)
    - Professional Portraits (Box 1)
    - Social Gatherings and Political Appearances (Box 1)